<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<notes>
Views are special classes that allow the generation of a custom class
diagram based on a set of diagram global options and a set of option
overrides for classes matching user specified conditions.

The <code>@view</code> tag, marks a class used to describe a single class diagram.
The general syntax for defining a view is:
<fmtcode ext="java">
/**
 * @view
 * @opt viewOption1
 * @opt viewOption2
 * ...
 * @match matchtype regularExpression
 * @opt option1.1 [argument]
 * @opt option1.2 [argument]
 * ...
 * @match matchtype regularExpression
 * @opt option2.1 [argument]
 * @opt option2.2 [argument]
 * ... 
 */
</fmtcode>

The @match tags allow to specify option overrides for classes that satisfy
the match condition. The match types are:
<ul>
<li><i>class</i>: matches class names using a regular expression.</li>
<li><i>subclass</i>: first looks for the base classes using the specified
regular expression, then matches the whole inheritance hierarchy of these
classes. The base classes are included in the match as well.</li>
<li><i>interface</i>: first looks for interfaces using the specified
regular expression, then matches every class that implements them, 
either directly or indirectly. The interfaces are included in the match
as well.</li>
<li><i>context</i>: looks for classes using a regular expression, 
then matches every class that's directly connected to them.</li>
</ul>

<p/>The <i>class</i> match type is intended to be used with a regular
expression, the others are usually performed against a class/interface
name rather than a real regular expression, but the syntax allows for
a regular expression to retain some flexibility (for example, a regular
expression can be used to match multiple classes, as in "(A|B|C)").<br/>
Refer to the <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html">Pattern</a> 
API docs for details on regular expression specifications.

<p/>Matches will be evaluted in the order of specification, each applying
its overrides to the current options. This means that options for a 
specific class are built in the following order, where each item overrides
only the options specified locally, leaving the other options intact:
<ul>
<li>Command line options</li>
<li>UMLOptions options</li>
<li>View options</li>
<li>Match overrides, in the order they are specified, and only for
the classes that satisfy the match conditions</li>
</ul>

<p/>Each view will generate a .dot file whose name is the name of the view,
unless the "output" option is specified to override it. Along with the "-views"
parameter on the command line, this allows for multiple views to be generated
in a single doclet invocation.

<h2>View inheritance</h2>

View classes can inherit from other view classes, allowing views to
share a set of common matches. The standard java inheritance mechanism
is used to specify inheritance.<br/>
Abstract view classes won't be used to generate diagrams, the common
idiom is to declare a base abstract view to share common options and
overrides, and have concrete view classes that extend for diagram generation.

<p/>When using view inheritance the option building order is:
<ul>
<li>Command line options</li>
<li>UMLOptions options</li>
<li>Base view options</li>
<li>View options</li>
<li>Base view match overrides</li>
<li>View match overrides</li>
</ul>
</notes>
